Another one was about IGF-1. Um I know
on the channel we haven't talked much
about IGF-1.
Um what are your thoughts on it? Um I
guess you don't recommend patients use
it.
>> You talking about the so like exogenous
IGF-1 or we talk
>> Yeah, I have this is something even in
the bodybuilding world that used to be
touted as like a that was the next
thing, right? that was going to be the
next big thing over GH. And I know IGF
can provide some benefits. I think a lot
of the majority of what I see are guys
getting better pumps in the gym and
things like that, fluid retention. I'm
like, well, how is that inducing fluid
retention? First of all, it's always a
good thing, right? You don't know the
mechanism in the body that's causing it
just because it gives you an advantage.
I haven't seen like I know I've had some
guys use IGF LR3. That's in the last few
years. I've not been very impressed with
what I've heard from them as far as bang
forbuck over something like
iipamearellin or something like that
that just seems to tick a few more
boxes. I'm not against it. Again, people
want to use these things. Go for it. See
what happens. I can't really re I don't
really prescribe the ones that haven't
been at least studied in humans very
much. Um and so I'm not that comfortable
doing that, but a lot of providers will.
Now, IGF-1 in general, that's the other
thing I wanted to talk about is people
get hoodwinkedked and get focused on
like baseline IGF levels and they try to
like make claims about, oh, I'm low. Oh,
I'm It's like these are also all over
the map and you can't tie and pin these
down to anything causitive in the body
at that time because it's just a
baseline. It's not how baseline labs
work. And so the best use for IGF, I
think in my opinion from a serum blood
testing standpoint, is usually just to
assess the value of the growth hormone
somebody's taking. Uh exogenous growth
hormone should typically show that rise
in IGF. I mean, that's what you see
people say to check if you want to see
if your GH is real, right? Um you don't
see those increases as much in guys on
the peptides, GHRPS and things like
that. But I tell guys that's okay. Like
they freak out about it. They think,
"Oh, because it's got the word growth
hormone releasing in it."
These are two different categories. And
I know this is going to get me in rabbit
trail territory with people. But people
don't understand the difference between
the exogenous substance being given and
studied and what happens versus the
claimed endogenous hormone that they
claim they're studying. If you actually
go look at how they study these things
originally,
you can't study that internal hormone
the way people think you can. What
they've done is they've derived these
hormones through chemical processes with
animal tissues or whatever, transformed
them into something that they then claim
is there originally, which may or may
not be true. But then they study those
man-made compounds, growth hormone,
whatever they've this precipitate that
was obtained from a dried up pituitary
gland that they did a lot of chemicals
to and called it growth hormone. Well,
why do they call it that? Because it
grew certain things in a petri dish or a
test tube. Same thing with IGF-1, right?
That's how they came up with the idea of
it is they noticed that putting GH into
these like tissue cultures would not
stimulate cartilage growth. But if you
took the serum of animals who had been
treated with growth hormone and you
applied that to these tissue cultures
that would induce cartilage growth. So
they were like, "Oh, there must be a
transformative property in the blood of
these GH given animals, right?" And
that's how I got its whole arc, right?
And that's fine because you're you're
kind of getting a coralate between
exogenous GH and then something in the
blood that you can call IGF-1 and what
that does as a downstream effect. Making
any claims about that from baseline
levels, none of that matters. Like you
just So all these people freaking out
saying, "Oh, IGF and cancer." It's like,
no, just because you can correlate
somebody's baseline IGF levels and say
people with cancer may have higher IGF
levels, that has nothing to do with
causation. The IGF-1 levels just maybe
increased because they already have
cancer or for some totally irrelevant
reasons. So, that's where I think I
wanted, you know, I harp on that a lot
and I don't know that many people think
about it like this, but they're just two
separate categories. Baseline levels are
over here. Levels via therapeutic
monitoring when a substance is given are
over here in this category. And these
are not the same. And that's that's just
the important thing. You know, I had a
guy come to see me and he's a biochemist
uh and he came to see me as a patient
>> and he started looking into the normal
ranges and he's like, you know, doc, I
couldn't believe it when I saw that
these ranges were not derived from
people taking the hormone because in his
world pharmaceuticals, you think about
therapeutic drug monitoring, drug
levels.
>> So in his mind, he was like, "That's how
this should have been done." And I'm
like, "Yeah, I know." But everybody just
goes off these normal ranges, which are
massive, 200 to 800, some nonsense.
Like, well, that's meaningless. Um, so I
just wanted to throw that out there that
these are two separate things. And I
don't want people to get hung up on the
IGF-1 baseline stuff as much as they do
because I think it causes unneeded
stress like most of these baseline labs
do. But if you want to take IGF as an
exogenous thing, again, you got to know
that what you're getting is real. We
don't know that with with half of these
things. If a compoundingy's making it,
it's probably legit from that
standpoint. But is IGF LR3 the same
thing as IGF that was taken 20 years ago
in the B, you know, I don't know. Um,
and people need to be careful with any
kind of these exogenous things because
we, again, you don't know what all
they're doing in the body. And as long
as you're okay with that, that's fine.
But I wouldn't push it on an
unsuspecting public who aren't going to
go in into all that and assess the
riskreward in their own life like a
bodybuilder would do.